when it comes to diet and cognitive
decline I've talked previously about
glycotoxins you know which are created
when high fat high protein foods are
exposed to high dry heat like broiling
or roasting in this video we look at
endotoxins which are inflammatory
components of bacteria that can end up
in our bloodstream how might the
presence of these toxins relate to
alzheimer's watch to find out
oh
[Music]
having a high cholesterol level in your
early 40s is associated with an
increased risk of Alzheimer's and
vascular dementia decades later and your
cholesterol doesn't have to be that high
to increase dementia risk of 57 percent
higher risk of developing Alzheimer's at
a total cholesterol of 240 compared to
under 200.
I've done a bunch of videos talking
about the clogging of the cerebral
arteries inside the brain with the same
atherosclerosis that causes heart
attacks and strokes choking off blood
flow to the memory centers in the brain
this may be why higher saturated fat
intake was found to be associated with
the development of worse Global
cognitive function and memory Decline
and apparent acceleration of brain aging
as if you were six years older
how can we cut down unsaturated fat by
cutting down on cheese cake ice cream
and chicken essentially at top sources
in the American diet but also pork
burgers and beef in general
in my video on the role of glycotoxins
and cognitive decline I profiled this
study showing that just five days of a
high fat low carb diet impairs energy
metabolism in the heart as well as
cognitive function concluding such diets
are detrimental to the heart and brain
now they were thinking the impaired
energy production may have accounted for
the brain dysfunction as well but high
levels of dietary glycotoxin so-called
ages are also associated with cognitive
decline so we may want to cut down our
intake of baked broiled or grilled meat
chicken or fish as well as certain dairy
products but there's another possibility
metabolic endotoxemia a potential
underlying mechanism of the relationship
between dietary fat intake and risk of
cognitive impairments
endotoxins are highly pro-inflammatory
components of certain types of bacteria
like E coli that are released when
bacteria die and can end up being
absorbed through our gut wall and end up
and our bloodstream resulting in What's
called endotoxemia the highest levels of
these endotoxins are found not
surprisingly in foods like meat that are
contaminated with bacteria both red meat
and white meat and having elevated
levels of endotoxins circulating your
bloodstream may be detrimental for
healthy aging associated with a large
range of diseases such as obesity type 2
diabetes heart disease and depression
put people on a high fat low carb diet
for five days and endotoxin levels in
the bloodstream roughly double endotoxin
levels before and after a few days on a
high fat diet
in fact even a single meal can do it
give people some sausage and Egg
McMuffins with hash browns and you can
get a significant increase within hours
after the meal how do we know it wasn't
the refined carbs in the muffin or
something because the control meal had a
muffin too but lower fat and no sausage
and egg in fact you can have people chug
straight sugar water no change in
endotoxin levels whereas there was a big
jump within hours drinking straight
cream which is pretty much straight fat
and not just any kind of fat but mostly
saturated fat a double blind randomized
crossover trial demonstrated a single
meal high in saturated fat can impede
attention meaning the cognitive ability
to distinguish Target stimuli from
distractors in a computer game compared
with an identical meal high in the kind
of fat found in nut seeds and avocados
and this cognitive deficit was present
five hours after the meal and who knows
how much longer after that there are two
ways to cut down on endotoxin bursts
after Meals one is to not eat so many in
the first place but if you do eat meat
and dairy the addition of fiber-rich
foods can Blunt The endotoxin Surge same
sausage and egg McMuffin endotoxin bomb
but with or without Fiber One cereal
which would be like 30 grams of fiber
and it seemed to glom onto the
endotoxins preventing the bump of
endotoxemia three hours after the meal
the fiber also reduced the oxidative
stress the free radicals generated by
such a meal showing clearly that the
addition of fiber to the high fat high
calorie meal had profound effects a
metabolic and inflammatory events after
the meal and over time a meal after meal
this could have long-term implications
recent investigations reported higher
abundance of endotoxins in the brains of
patients with Alzheimer's disease on
autopsy endotoxins building up in the
memory center of the brain the region of
the brain that develops the earliest and
most profound neural pathology in
Alzheimer's
some Advanced Alzheimer's patients had
up to a 26-fold increase in endotoxin
levels over age match controls without
dementia and where were the endotoxins
concentrated
smack dab in the middle of the amyloid
plaques a pathology characteristic of
Alzheimer's the endotoxins are standing
red here and the amyloid standing green
you can see how they superimpose right
over each other suggesting endotoxins
may be playing a role in the formation
of these plaques like happens in the
brains of other animals for these and
other reasons proper nutrition has been
proposed as a promising non-medical
strategy to prevent cognitive decline
and subsequent dementia
foreign